# Henrique Sposito

#### COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENTIST

☑ henrique.sposito@graduateinstitute.ch | ☆ henriquesposito.com | ② 0000-0003-3420-6085 | ☑ henriquesposito

### Profile

My research leverages advanced text analysis techniques, such as supervised machine learning, to investigate how authenticity, problem construction, and urgency appear and change over time and across settings in political discourses. I also develop, contribute, and help maintain several R packages that assist researchers dealing with multiple, overlapping, and uncertain datasets across various domains of global governance.

Interests: Political Sociology, Environmental Studies, Statistical Methods, Text Analysis, Comparative Politics

### Education

#### PhD in International Relations and Political Science

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES

 Doctoral Project: 'Authenticity, problem construction, and urgency in political discourses' Supervised by Dr. James Hollway and Dr. Yanina Welp

### Masters in International Relations and Political Science

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES

• Masters' Thesis: 'The Construction of a Migrant Crisis - The Venezuelan Migration to Brazil' Supervised by Dr. Melanie Kolbe and Dr. Graziella Moraes Silva

### Bachelor of Arts in Political Science and Sociology (Double Degree)

UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA AT BIRMINGHAM

• Recipient of 4 years of scholarship as a Student-Athlete for Soccer in a NCAA Division 1 University

Geneva, Switzerland

Sep 2019 - 2024 (expected)

Geneva, Switzerland Sep 2017 - Aug 2019

Birmingham, United States

Jan 2013 - Jun 2017

### **Selected Employment History**

### **Centre for International Environmental Studies**

Geneva, Switzerland

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Sep 2020 - Present

- Assist with the theoretical, methodological, and empirical developments in data and analysis for across various domains of global governance in the 'PANARCHIC: Power and Networks and the Rate of Change in Institutional Complexes' project funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation
- Help with the development data infrastructure and statistical methods in R, offered as an emsemble of R packages, for the gathering, consolidating, and analyzing global governance data
- Train and manage research assistants to work with data colletion, R package development, GitHub branching, website design, and among other programmatic issues related to the project

IntersoccerGeneva, SwitzerlandFOOTBALL HEAD COACHMay 2018 - Aug 2020

- Ensured a safe and constructive environment for participants, coaches, and parents while promoting the benefits of sports
- Supervised coaches and participants throughout activities to ensure their safety
- Communicated with coaches, children, and parents to cordinate and solve logistical issues related to transportation, venue organization, and delivery of supplies, as well as any medical emergencies and other unexpected events that arose

### **Publications and Working Papers**

Which Amazon Problem? Problem-constructions and Transnationalism in Brazilian Presidential Discourse since 1985 (with Livio Silva-Muller)

**Environmental Politics** 

June 2023

Radiating Truthiness: Authenticity performances in politics in Brazil and the United States

FORTHCOMING IN POLITICAL STUDIES

DOI: 10.1080/09644016.2023.2220639

# Promises Promises: An introduction to urgency analyzis (with Jael Tan and James Hollway)

WORKING PAPER

### Managing imprecise dates in R with messydates (with James Hollway)

WORKING PAPER

### Teaching.

#### Fundamentals of R (co-lecturer)

Fall 2022, Spring 2023, Fall 2023

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES

- · Provides a hands-on introduction to data science using the R programming language and software
- Teaches students how to import, transform, analyze, and visualize various types of data in R
- · Demonstrates practical applications of R for the analysis of environment, finance, and conflict data

### **Intermediate R for Social Science Research**

Fall 2023

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES

- Provides an applied introduction to various research methods using R
- Teaches students how to select and carry-on different types of statistical modeling; how to work with unsupervised approaches for text analysis; and how to analyze and visualize survey data

### Conference Presentations

### Anti-PC and Authenticity: Authenticity performances in politics in Brazil and the United States

Los Angeles, United States

AMERICAN SOCIOLOGICAL ASSOCIATION

August 2022

• Regular session on the 'Party and its base: Understanding the relationship between political professionals and their audiences'

### Amazonian Repertoires in Brazilian Presidential Discourse since 1985

Online

**LATIN AMERICAN STUDIES ASSOCIATION** 

May 2022

• Panel on the 'Forest Managements Conservation and Agricultural Production'

## Performing Authenticity: Anti-Politically Correct Discourses in Brazil and the United States

Online

SWISS POLITICAL SCIENCE ASSOCIATION

February 2022

• Workshop session on 'Liberal Ideology and Cultural Backlash'

### The Construction of a Migratory Crisis: The Venezuelan Migration to Brazil

Online

LATIN AMERICAN STUDIES ASSOCIATION

May 2020

• Panel on 'Las distintas violencias de las migraciones'

### **Invited Talks**

# How has the Brazilian Amazon been Constructed as a Problem? Presidential Speeches and Transnational Politics since 1985

Geneva, Switzerland

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES

October 2022

• Invited talk at the Centre for International Environmental Studies Seminar

# Anti-Political Correctness and Authenticity: Authenticity performances in politics in Brazil and the United States

Lausanne, Switzerland

• Invited talk for the Research Group on Elections and Political Citizenship

March 2022

### **RPackages**

Université de Lausanne

manydata Contributor

AN R PORTAL FOR GLOBAL GOVERNANCE DATA

messydates Contributor

AN R PACKAGE FOR EXTENDED DATE/TIME FORMAT

manynet Contributor

An R package to make, manipulate, and map myriad networks

migraph Contributor

AN R PACKAGE WITH TOOLS FOR MULTIMODAL AND MULTILEVEL NETWORK ANALYSIS

**poldis** Author

AN R PACKAGE WITH TOOLS FOR ANALYZING POLITICAL DISCOURSES OVER TIME

manypkgs Contributor

AN R PACKAGE TO SUPPORT THE CREATION OF NEW MANY PACKAGES

manyenviron Contributor

AN R DATA PACKAGE ON ENVIRONMENTAL AGREEMENTS

**manystates** Contributor

AN R DATA PACKAGE ON SOVEREIGN STATES

### **Awards and Honors**

Best Paper in Amazonian Studies at the Latin American Studies Association for "Which Amazon Problem?
 Problem-constructions and Transnationalism in Brazilian Presidential Discourse since 1985"

- UAB Presidential Honors List 2013, 2015, 2016 and 2017
- Conference USA Commissioner's Honor Roll 2013 2016
- National Soccer Coaches Association of America NCAA Scholar All-South Region Team 2016
- Conference USA All-Academic Team 2016
- College Sports Information Directors of America Academic All-District Team 2016
- Conference USA Academic Honor Medal 2015

### Skills\_

- Languages: Portuguese (native); English (fluent); French (proficient); Italian (intermediate); Spanish (basic)
- Programming languages: R (proficient); Python (intermediate); C (basic); Bash (basic); Java (basic)
- Markup languages: Markdown (proficient); LaTeX (advanced); HTML (advanced); CSS (advanced)

### References\_

#### James Hollway

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR OF INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS AND POLITICAL SCIENCE

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES

• Email: james.hollway@graduateinstitute.ch

### Graziella Moraes Dias da Silva

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR OF ANTHROPOLOGY AND SOCIOLOGY

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES

• Email: graziella.moraes@graduateinstitute.ch

### Yanina Welp

RESEARCH FELLOW

ALBERT HIRSCHMAN CENTRE ON DEMOCRACY

• Email: yanina.welp@graduateinstitute.ch